Guide to the Workers Education Bureau of America Records 1920-1954
Workers Education Bureau of America Records
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
Workers Education Bureau of America Records, 1920-1954
5277
Workers Education Bureau of America
2 linear ft.
Bibliographies, reports (documents).
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
Consist of governance and financial documents, reports, correspondence, memoranda and notes pertaining to radio programs, courses and programs to promote workers' education, adult and vocational schools and educational programs (1921-1951).
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Founded in 1921 by a group of unionists and educators, the Workers' Education Bureau of America (WEB) functioned under the directorship of Spencer Miller and John D. Conners as a service organization for research, teaching, publication, and extension work in workers' education. WEB received financial, political, and consultative support from American Federation of Labor (A.F. of L.) leaders, including Samuel Gompers, William Green, and Matthew Woll. In 1951, WEB was formally integrated into the A.F. of L. as its Education Department.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Section 1. History: Records consist mainly of correspondence, memoranda, and reports pertaining to the routine administration and activities of the Workers' Education Bureau of America. Organizational records include financial statements and auditors' reports (1922- 1947); bibliographies; reading lists; clippings; and certificates of incorportation and certification. Also, memoranda, letters and reports pertaining to the Labor Book Fund; workers' education programs in various states; the Federal Emergency Relief Administration-WEB jointly sponsored West Coast School of Unemployed Workers (1934); the WEB-A.F. of L. dispute with Brookwood Labor School (1929); financial matters; the establishment of a labor correspondence school, the International Labor News Service for Worker Education, the Pittsburgh Labor College, and the A.F. of L. Education Department.
Includes correspondence chiefly of Spencer Miller and John D. Conners with Samuel Gompers and William Green (presidents, A.F. of L.) and Matthew Woll (vice president, A.F. of L.); the American Association of Adult Education; William Haber (professor, Michigan State College); William J. Bowen (president, Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers' International Union of America); Victor A. Olander (secretary-treasurer, Illinois State Federation of Labor); and Fannia M. Cohn (secretary, International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union) pertaining to the Workers' Education Bureau Press Inc., workers' education, A.F. of L.-WEB relations and joint programs, and leadership training.
Section 2. Organizational activities: Records consist of memoranda, reports, correspondence and miscellaneous documents pertaining to WEB relations with the A.F. of L.; various workers' education programs conducted by unions, academia, and government agencies; and the founding and development of WEB. Include documents pertaining to the establishment of the Labor Book Fund (1922-1928). Also, reports, memoranda and notes pertaining to vocational, adult, and workers' education programs in various states (1935-1939); A.F. of L-WEB joint conferences on labor and public education; Rutgers University-New Jersey Federation of Labor-WEB joint conferences on international labor relations (1946-1947); and Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS) workers' education radio broadcasts (1939). Additionally, correspondence of Spencer Miller with Harry Russell (director, WEB, New England Region) on regional conferences and programs (1925-1928); of Sterling Fisher (director of educational radio talks, CBS) on research and radio broadcasts (1939); and of William Green on workers' education programs in academia (1935).
Also, correspondence of John D. Conners with Harold Taylor (president, Sarah Lawrence College) on Fulbright Scholarships, and worker and student exchange programs with Ruskind College, Oxford Univ., and with Matthew Woll on WEB and A.F. of L. cooperative projects and workers' education programs. Also, correspondence of Woll (in the capacity of labor chairman, National Advisory Council on Radio in Education) with William Green and President Franklin D. Roosevelt regarding WEB radio broadcasts (1932).
Section 3. Publications and research documents: Consist of reading lists and bibliographies; published and unpublished pamphlets and reports; notes, memoranda, and manuscript drafts of reports on research projects; and news releases and bulletins of WEB and various cooperating agencies. Include materials by Samuel Gompers, Edward C. Lindeman, Theresa Wolfson, John D. Conners, Mark Starr, Fannia Cohn, Nelson H. Cruikshank, and Arthur Elder pertaining to workers' education; public speaking; child labor; leadership training; collective bargaining; voluntary unionism; the history of the A.F. of L.; labor plays; social security; unemployment; workmen's compensation; labor and the economy; labor history; unions and the community; the construction industry; and the international labor relations programs conducted by the American Council of Education and the American Friends Service Committee.
Section 4. Miscellaneous correspondence and reports: Consist chiefly of published and unpublished reports; routine correspondence of Spencer Miller and John D. Conners; and notes and memoranda. Materials regard workers' education and the atomic age, international labor problems, leadership training, radio programs, technology and unemployment, regional workers' education programs, teacher training, and unemployment (1921-1951).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bowen, William J.; Cohn, Fannia M. (Fannia May), 1888-1962.; Conners, John D.; Cruikshank, Nelson H.; Elder, Arthur H.; Fisher, Sterling; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Green, William, 1872-1952; Lindeman, Eduard; Miller, Spencer, 1891-; Olander, Victor A., 1873-1949; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882- 1945; Russell, Harry A.; Starr, Mark, 1894-; Taylor, Harold, 1947; Wolfson, Theresa, 1897-1972; Woll, Matthew, 1880-1956; American Association for Adult Education; Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers International Union of America; Brookwood Labor College; Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc.; Illinois State Federation of Labor; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; New Jersey State Federation of Labor; Ruskind College (University of Oxford); Rutgers University; United States. Federal Emergency Relief Administration.; West Coast School of Unemployed Workers; Workers' Education Bureau of America; Workers' Education Bureau Press, inc.
Subjects:
Adult education teachers, Training of--United States.; Child labor--United States.; Construction industry--United States.; Educational exchanges--United States.; Press, Labor--United States.; Radio in adult education--United States.; Social security--United States.; Unemployment--United States.; Unemployment, Technological--United States.; Vocational education--United States.; Workers' compensation--United States.; Adult education teachers; Labor and laboring classes. Education. United States.; Labor and laboring classes. United States. Drama.; Trade-union leadership. United States.; Trade-unions. United States. Social activity.; Unemployment relief. United States.; Workers' education. United States.; Workers' education. United States. Curricula.
Form and Genre Terms:
Bibliographies.; Reports (documents)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
CONTAINER LIST
- Articles of Incorporation (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Auditor's Reports, 1922-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
- Auditor's Reports, 1921-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Worker's Education Bureau Press, Inc.
- Copyright Registrations, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Financial Correspondence, 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes correspondence from Matthew Woll, Fifth Vice-President, American Federation of Labor and Peter J. Brady, President, Federation Bank and Trust Company on routine matters (1927); letter from F. P. Keppel, President, Carnegie Corporation, praising the Bureau (1928); financing plan outline from Will McCord, The Organization Finance Bureau.
- Financial Correspondence, 1929-1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Contains correspondence from Haley Fiske, President, Metropolitan Life Insurance Co. on routine matters (1929); two letters from Franklin D. Roosevelt, Vice-President, Fidelity and Deposit Trust Company of Maryland praising the objectives of the Bureau (1925) and declining to make a fund raising appeal in the newspapers (1925); correspondence from Dr. Frederick D. Keppel, President, Carnegie Corporation regarding grant application and approval (1932); grant approval notification from W.W. Brierly, Secretary, General Education Board (1934); letter from William Green, President, American Federation of Labor regarding increased contribution (1937); undated loan agreement signed by several members of the Executive Committee of the Bureau.
- General Correspondence, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes letter from Samuel Gompers, President, American Federation of Labor and correspondence with Florence Thorne, American Federation of Labor on routine matters; suggestions from W. H. Manwaring, The Labor College regarding proposed structure of Bureau courses (5 pp, handwritten).
- General Correspondence, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Contains correspondence from Florence Thorne, American Federation of Labor regarding articles of agreement between the American Federation of Labor and the Worker's Education Bureau (3 pp typed, 4 handwritten); letter from Matthew Wall, President, International Photo-Engraver's Union regarding the election of executive board chairman; critique of agreement by J. M. Budish, Editor, The Headgear Worker; "American Federation of Labor and Worker's Education", stenographic report of Matthew Woll, Chairman, Education Committee, American Federation of Labor and excerpt of Samuel Gomper's speech delivered at the Second Annual Conference Worker's Education Bureau; letter from Gompers regarding formation of joint executive board; correspondence with Florence Thorne on routine matters; letter from Gompers naming representatives to Executive Committee.
- General Correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes form letter from Matthew Woll urging affiliates to form permanent education committees (2pp, 1924); and routine (1923); routine correspondence with Florence Thorne; proposal to assist in developing labor legislation in Nicaragua from Chester M. Wright, English Language Secretary, Pan American Federation of Labor (1924).
- General Correspondence, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Contains correspondence from Florence Thorne regarding labor research and routine matters; Oliver Carlson, Director, Worker's School application for affiliation (and subsequent denial); letter of appreciation from William Green on general labor research; notes and suggestions on a variety of issues connected with the Bureau possibly from Lloyd Cosgrave (12pp handwritten).
- General Correspondence, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Includes routine correspondence with Florence Thorne; letter of praise to Matthew Woll from Herbert Hoover, Secretary, Department of Commerce.
- General Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Contains requests of Grace B. Kleug, Chairman, Educational Committee of the Ladies Auxilllary, International Association of Machinists for advice on initiating an education program; routine correspondence from William Green; letter opposing limiting membership of Executive Committee from Fannia Cohn, Executive Secretary, Education Department International Ladies Garment Workers Union; letter praising the commencement of regularly scheduled conferences from William Green.
- General Correspondence, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Includes correspondence from James H. Maurer, Superintendent, Department of Accounts and Finance (Reading, PA) reluctantly agreeing to remain President of the Worker's Education Bureau (1928)
- General Correspondence, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Includes correspondence and attachments with William Green concerning preliminary plan for developing a Department of Education within the American Federation of Labor (1931).
- General Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Contains queries from the executive officers of the Bureau regarding the continued solvency of the Bureau; correspondence with Frances Perkins, Secretary of Labor regarding establishing an Education Department within the Labor Department; affiliation fee from David Dubinsky, President, International Ladies Garment Worker's Union; letter regarding funds for Bureau run labor institutes from Horse A. Cartwright, Director, American Association for Adult, Education.
- General Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Statement given by Thomas E. Burke, President, Workers Education Bureau, at a conference called by the Secretary of Labor and the Commissioner of Education (1934); correspondence with Peter J. Burke regarding the anticipated affiliation of the Worker's Education Council of New York City (1934); correspondence from William Green regarding the Western Labor College (1935).
- General Correspondence, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- General Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Includes routine correspondence from William Green(1939); letter of praise from George Meany, Secretary-Treasurer, American Federation of Labor (1941); four photographs labeled "WEB 20th Anniversary-April 1941".
- General Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Contains correspondence with Mark Starr, Chairman, Labor Advisory Council, Worker's Service Program, WPA regarding the beginning of the Labor Extension Service under the auspices of the U.S. Department of Labor; letter from C.J. Haggerty, President, California Federation of Labor refusing to participate in programs offered by the People's Educational Center; letter from William Wolff, Executive Secretary, People's Educational Center outlining organization and objective.
- General Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Includes letter from Glen Burch, Editor Adult Education Journal regardinq postwar activities (1946); correspondence with Florence Thorne, Director of Research, American Federation of Labor regarding suggestions on the Labor Extension Service (1946); routine correspondence with Matthew Woll, Chairman, Committee on Education, American Federation of Labor (1946); routine correspondence from Walter G. O'Donnell, Chairman, Adult Education Committee, American Federation of Teachers, Local 279 (1946).
- "History of the Worker's Education Bureau" Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Positions of Employment, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
- Positions of Employment, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 27-29)
- Correspondence School Institute, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Includes plan outline for Organization of Washington Labor Institute from Richard S. Harvey, Lawyer.
- Labor Book Fund, 1922-1931 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Contains several letters from Fannia Cohn in her capacity as a trustee of the Labor Text Book Fund (1922, 1928, 1929).
- Labor Schools, 1922-1941 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Includes a refusal to contribute from William L. Hutcheson, General President, United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America (1927); Correspondence with John Brophy regarding his membership on the Executive Board (1927); routine correspondence from James H. Maurer and Thomas E. Burke (1927); letter from William Green regarding the denial of affiliation to the Union Labor College of Pittsburgh (1928), letter from William Collins, General Organizer, American Federation of Labor, regarding John Brophy and the removal of his endorsement by the Pittsburgh Central Labor Union (1928).
- National Civic Federation, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  A Brief History of the Origin Development and Present Activities of the National Civic Federation typescript, 22pp.
- New England Division, 1928-1936 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Routine Correspondence with Harry A. Russell, Regional Director, Worker's Education Bureau (1928, 1929, 1934, 1935); routine correspondence with Nelson Cruikshank of Connecticut (1935); routine correspondence with William Green (1935); letter from Harry A. Russell regarding program implementation (1928).
- Radio Programs, 1931-1938 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Includes program agenda and selected script for "The People's Platform" which aired weekly from July 20, 1938 to April 23, 1939; program agenda and selected script for "Americans at Work" a program aired weekly from April 28, 1938 to April 15, 1939; correspondence with Sterling Fisher, Director of Education and Radio Talks, Columbia Broadcasting System regarding decision to discontinue research services of the Bureau (1939); routine correspondence front Levering Tyson, Director, National Advisory Council on Radio in Education (1934); letter to Matthew Woll from Franklin D. Roosevelt, Governor, State of New York, praising the radio series (1932); letter from William Green praising radio programs (1932).
- Ruskin College Scholarships, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  Includes routine correspondence from Harold Taylor, Chairman, Committee on Ruskin Labor Scholarships (1947).
- Rutgers Institute, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 38-40)
- Teacher Training, 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Contains routine correspondence from Matthew Woll, Seventh Vice-president, American Federation of Labor(1923); letter to Lloyd Crosgrave, Assistant Secretary, Worker's Education Bureau regarding the Gary system from F. G. Stecker, Secretary-Treasurer, American Federation of Teachers (1926),
- Unemployment, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- UNESCO, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Contains travel authorization for John D. Connors, President, Worker's Education Bureau, to the meeting of the Committee on Education of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
- University Extension, 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Vocational Education, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Western Division, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  Includes routine correspondence from E. W. Mounce, State Supervisor of Worker's Education Bureau in Missouri (1935); routine correspondence with Paul Vogt, Western Regional Director, Worker's Education Bureau (1935); tentative draft of Worker's Forum from Paul Vogt (1935).
- Worker's Education Bureau Press, Inc., 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Worker's Education Bureau Press, Inc., 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  Includes correspondence from Chester M. Wright, Editor, International Labor News Service regardinq joint venture with the Bureau (1927); criticisms of "Trade Unionism in the Building Industry" from William J. McSorley, President, Building Trades Department, American Federation of Labor and William J. Bowen, President, Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers Union of America (1927); routine correspondence from William Green (1928).
- Worker's Education Bureau Press, Inc., 1929-1935 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Contains correspondence concerning the litigation Fleming & Reavley vs. The Worker's Education Bureau (1929); Victor C. Olander, Secretary-Treasurer, Illinois Federation of Labor critique of pamphlet (1931).
- Worker's Education Bureau Press, Inc., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  Correspondence regarding Samuel Hasanovitch and his unauthorized us of Bureau credentials for the purpose of personal gain.
- Worker's Education Bureau Spring Conference, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Annual Reports, 1935-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Article Series, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  "The Pros and Cons of Consumer Credit" by Constance Kent, 16pp. typescript
- Article Series, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  "Labor in the Postwar World" by Dr. John L. Childs, 4pp. reprint
- Article Series, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  "Labor's Stake Abroad" by Dr. William Withers, 6pp, reprint "Labor and Social Security" by Nelson Cruikshank, 6 pp, photocopied reprint
- Article Series, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  "Workers Education: What? Why? How?" by John D. Connors, 18pp (12pp typescript, 6pp photocopy) "Money and How It Works" by Jerry Voorhis, 6 pp, (5pp photocopy, 1p reprint).
- Article Series, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  "Workers Interdependence in Our Economy" by Arthur A. Elder, 6pp, reprint (plus additional typescript, reprint and photocopies)
- Article Series (Box 2, Folder 7)
  "Sweden: Laboratory in Economic Democracy" by Arnold S. Zander, 17 pp, typescript (plus additional reprints)
- Article Series, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  "Labor and the Law" by Matthew Woll, 6pp, reprint "Organized Labor's Stake in Tax Policy" by Arthur A, Elder, 6pp, reprint.
- Article Series, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  "Labor and UNESCO" by John D. Connors, 6pp, reprint (plus additional reprints) "The Soviet System - of Mind Control" by George S. Counts, 3pp. Reprint
- Crosgrave Article Series, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  "Short Stories on Economics", 12pp. typescript.
- Crosgrave Article Series, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  "More Short Stories on Economics", 12pp. typescript.
- Crosgrave Article Series, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  "National Defence", 13 pp, typescript. "More on National Defense", 12pp, typescript,
- Crosgrave Article Series, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  "America at War", 13pp, typescript, "The World at War", part I-VI, 13 pp, typescript.
- Crosgrave Article Series, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  "The World at War", part VII-XII, 12pp, typescript. "After the War", 12pp, typescript
- Labor Lecture Series, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Pamphlets
- Libraries, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Includes correspondence from William Green regarding opportunity for the American Federation of Labor and the American Library Association to cooperate.
- Miscellaneous Publications, 1926-1936 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Miscellaneous Publications, 1946-1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Pamphlets, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
- Pamphlet Series, 1921-1925 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Pamphlet Series, 1926-1933 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Pamphlet Series, 1934-1946 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Picket History of the AFL-CIO, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Original, manuscript
- Press Releases, 1935-1947 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Railway Review, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Reading List Series, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Research, 1924-1928 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Research, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  Routine correspondence with Dr. Carole Blume, Dr. Mollie Ray Carol/ Director of Research and Ursula Batchelder Stone.
- Research, 1947-1950 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Research Division Pamphlets, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Research Division Series, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Shop Stewards Manual, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Contains original typescript and sketches
- Shop Stewards Manual, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Manuscript
- Syllabus Series Pamphlets, 1920-1926 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Syllabus Series Pamphlets, 1935-1945 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Workers Education News Service, 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  11pp, miscellaneous reprints